everyone and thank you for joining
joining the consistent compounders
webinar
uh you know we have with us raksha
and saurabh is also joining
we will follow our user usual process of
conducting the webinar which is rakshith
saurabh to give us an update on the fun
and i will also request them to share
their initial thoughts on our latest ccp
newsletter
uh you know which we published earlier
this month studying the holiday schedule
of consistent compounders share price
now after their initial thoughts we will
open the house for q a
request all of you to please keep
posting your queries on q and a box
raksha floor is yours rakshitsara flores
thank you
hi good evening everyone thank you for
uh
logging in
so let me
once again um can you enable screen
sharing for me please
yeah thank you
okay
all right so um i mean it's uh it's
volatile times it's turbulent times in
the stock market uh
uh uh
from october to uh march
uh there was a period of uh
sort of market delivering broadly uh
not much and we underperforming by
by a good six seven percentage points
during the six-month period from october
21 to
march 31 uh last month uh there was a
there was a little bit of two percentage
point alpha
uh and last couple of days of this month
have again been again been quite
volatile in absolute terms
um so on in that context uh uh i mean
while we have discussed in the past the
reasons why
october to march there was a there was
an underperformance at the portfolio
level and i'll touch upon those reasons
again as a summary um towards the end of
this presentation but also uh it's worth
understanding
a stock level a stock specific level
uh
stagnation in the share price as well
which is not necessarily just linked to
the last six months but in some cases
uh has been ongoing for the last say one
two years so for instance an htfc bank a
nestle
uh an hdfc life right these are three
examples from our cons consistent
compounders portfolio
where
not just in the last six months but
actually for the bulk of the last one
one and a half year
we've had not much of uh performance of
the share price for these companies and
hence uh valid questions have been asked
by our clients
around why do we stay convinced and why
do we keep holding on to these companies
when the share prices haven't been
forming um even prior to october 21 when
the rest of the portfolio was was
delivering pretty healthy absolute
returns um so
so in that regard uh
uh we thought it's uh it's best we
we answer this question by by referring
to some uh empirical evidence from
historical uh share price performance of
various companies in our portfolio
and
and we call it the holiday schedule so
let's start off with
start off with asian paints right this
is
a chart showing
uh the last
12 years of
share price trajectory of
asian paints now
uh point to point as in jan 2010 to
april 22
jan 2010 to april 2022 dashing paints
has delivered a
share price compounding of 26 cagr and
hence uh
anybody looking at this chart in
hindsight would have uh would have
called it a
called it a great
and consistent compounder and
would have been very comfortable holding
on to the stock in the portfolio uh when
this stock delivered 26
annualized rate of compounding over a 12
long year period right effectively
becoming becoming uh 10 year 10x in 10
years
at a 26 cagr and that run rate has been
has been displayed
on this chart over the last 12 years but
having said that there were these three
encircled periods
over the last 12 uh
12 years where
for a good one one and a half two year
period
asian painter's share price didn't do
anything
right so
would you have been
questioning the investment in asian
paints at that time if you were a
shareholder
depends on what was happening behind the
scenes
if behind the scenes the fundamentals
were weak
then probably
without any foresight on how the share
price chart is going to progress you
should have been worried
if behind the scenes the the
fundamentals were progressing really
well
then despite the stagnation in the
shared price performance of asian paints
over these 12 15 18 month periods
you should have been quite comfortable
so that's the that's the broad theme of
the three bubbles and let's go through
them maybe one by one so this is the
first instance
where uh where between july 10
and december 11
the concerns that
investors had when the share price
delivered zero
uh were around first and foremost
massive input cost inflation and its
impact on margins if you remember
between july 10 and december 11 crude
oil prices more than doubled
right not only did the prices double
tio2
titanium dioxide which is
one of the largest raw material inputs
into paint manufacturing processes
tio2 underwent a massive shortage of
supply
that was in addition to overall raw
material cost inflation right and in
order to offset these types of
procurement challenges
asian paints did was for two consecutive
years they hiked their product prices by
twelve to fifteen percent each and uh
these were fy eleven and fy twelve two
consecutive years
uh they hide product prices by
12 to 15 percent each and the concern
that investors at that time had
were that will this not lead to a
moderation in
in volume growth because
there is price elasticity of demand once
the price increases are of
disproportionately higher degree such as
a 12 to 15 percent remember over the
last 25 years annual average price
increase taken up by asian fans is only
two percent
right against a two percent 25 year
average
during those two years there was a 12 to
15 percent
price increase annually taken right so
those were the concerns the share price
didn't do much
in fact behind the scenes if you had
peaked into the fundamentals
uh they had a massive
sort of 18 20 percent cagr in the
in the dealership count expansion uh at
the same time a massive automation of
their uh of the manufacturing plants was
underway which in hindsight now we enjoy
because
free cash flow compounding of asian
paints as a result ended up being
significantly higher than even the even
the rate of revenue growth of profit
growth
and
all of these
investments were not only in the back
end there were several tech investments
being done
around salesforce automation at the
front end as well and they were the
first first of the kind in the industry
at that time
and quite disruptive in that regard
as a result
had you been holding on to asian paints
during that time in the next
12 months
after this holiday period of
july 10 to december 11
in the next 12 months asian paints
delivered an absolute return
of 70
zero
right so after the 259 rupees share
price that you see
in uh in december december 11
the calendar year 12 saw
saw 70 percent increase in the share
price of asian feds effectively
the stock caught up on the
sluggish share price performance period
and it caught up with the fundamental
progression right so that's uh that was
the first example
uh second time it happened uh
this was more around jan 15 to april
april 16.
um the concerns here were that there
were two consecutive
back-to-back weak monsoons that india
had seen and that was affecting consumer
demand across all sorts of sectors
including
uh home building industry right home
building materials industry and the
concern was will that affect
fundamentals of asian paints adversely
or not
right at the same time
uh crude oil price had started falling
now uh intuitively you would have
thought if crude oil price was falling
investors should have been happy about
margin expansion but here asian paints
in order to not leave any room
for competition to get a breathing space
asian paints took
chunky price cuts
in fy fy 16 and those price cuts uh led
to investor concerns around whether
asian paints does have any pricing power
to hold on to
uh expansion and margins when input cost
deflation
is uh is the is the ongoing phenomenon
right so so that's uh
that's in effect the the reason why the
share price didn't do much
during that time uh
but behind the scenes again massive
dealer network expansion uh massive
investment in technology and uh
launch of a very disruptive concept
which today has started picking up base
uh around home decor around uh ap homes
as a retail network so on and so forth
right so so the company was not
getting worried management was not
getting worried about
any
pricing power oriented piece about
related to their price cuts or monsoon
demand after week monsoon etc if you
held on to asian paints
during this time
in the next 12 months the share price
delivered more than 30 percent
uh return right after this 866
point in the next 12 months the share
price delivered more than 30 percent
return and caught up with fundamentals
again right likewise
um for the gst period right may 17 to
april 18 and remember asian pains
has been at the
center of
gst as a as a new disrupter because
dealer would be selling paint
prior to gst
to the contractor or the painter right
transition
into all being a formalized economy uh
at the front end formalized distribution
network at the front end was a massive
concern along with that crude oil prices
were rising they again doubled crude oil
prices doubled roughly around this
period and jsw paints announced uh their
entry into the paint industry with a
with a new concept of a single price
point several sku so on and so forth
right so from from a variety of uh
angles they were in investor concerns
and during this 12 month period
there was no share price movement at all
right at that time
we were running
at a different platform we were running
a pms and
and asian paints was one of the larger
holdings and this share price didn't
move in that pms right
behind the scenes
massive uh expansion of capacities was
underway they nearly doubled their
capacity through the launch of visage
and mysore plants uh they entered into
uh putti waterproofing
in a way gave the cement companies
uh head-on competition in putti industry
gave pedilite
dr fix it a lot of competition in the
waterproofing industry and
gained a lot of market share in both of
these
new segments
thereafter
including in decorative paints what
would have happened had you held on to
asian paints after the holiday period
got over
the share price delivered a
eleven percent
uh absolute return in the next three
years right in the next three years
delivered a hundred and uh eleven
percent absolute return
right uh that's more like a thirty
percent cagr right and again more than
catching up on the lost
uh lost momentum
during may 2017 to april 18 right
likewise now i'll go a little faster
probably you've got the theme what's
playing out here dr lyle path labs after
its listing for the first three years
delivered
a holiday to its investors right
absolutely no progression in the share
price
but behind the scenes
they managed to
massively avert
a price war from thyrocare and still
continue growing
in ncr region and expanded into into the
eastern territory which today has become
a very formidable profitable part of dr
lal's overall portfolio and it has
de-risked dr lal from being only north
india exposed right uh that was what dr
lal was doing when the shared price was
doing not doing anything it was as long
as almost a three-year period right but
once that three-year period was over
dr lal delivered an annualized return
annualized return of eighty percent
right in the in the next couple of years
right uh so that's how these share
prices they catch up with
with the lost momentum and including the
recent fall of dr lal
point to point this chart has delivered
more than 20 annualized return right so
including this fall of the last six
months and including the stagnation of
three years
in the last six year period dr lars
share price has had
more than 20 annualized analyzed return
that's the reward for holding on to it
uh if you couldn't time the entry exit
precisely right
this is pretty light very similar to
asian paints
two periods of stagnation when asian
paints also saw similar uh piece where
first of all there was massive raw
material cost inflation in fy 12. it
light also hiked prices behind the
scenes the company did
a complete transformation on tech
investments and
and massive product launches
and you can see what happened to the
share price from 167 in in july 12 the
share price moved on to 600 by jan 15
right after a period of stagnation the
next three years saw
a forex increase in the
in the share price right
that was followed by another period of
stagnation um similar reasons where
volume growth had slowed down because of
a couple of weak monsoons
right
and
there was also also uh
the concern around pricing part because
pedolite also took price cuts when crude
oil price fell during this period but uh
massive uh uh work being done behind the
scenes once the holiday period was over
you can see what happened after 603 to
the next three four years of share price
trajectory right exponential in a way
you can put it
um so so this is what happens uh just to
remind people that this is not just the
last 10 years
even in the preceding decade as in 2000
to 2007 before the global financial
crisis we used to see this sort of a
phenomenon this is hdfc bank
for three long years there was zero
share price return right
in fact negative negative three percent
as the chart shows uh despite the fact
that over this three year period
profit after tax of hdfc bank it
compounded at 48 cagr right once the
holiday period was over
hdfc bank's
share price delivered a 42 cagr in the
next three years and hence more than
caught up more than caught up with the
sluggishness reported during the holiday
period right um so that's what
keeps happening right now as i mentioned
previously we've got three stocks in our
consistent compounders portfolio where
even if you ignore the last six years of
overall
uh a sort of sluggish return for the
portfolio as a whole these three stocks
in particular have had a longer than 12
month
holiday going on at the share price
level
the concerns are different for different
companies for nestle the concern is well
the the input cost inflation what does
it do to margins volume growth
uh
is is coming in maggie in chocolates but
it is not coming in baby foods for the
last couple of years
what are we
heading towards when
baby foods is more than half of the
portfolio for nestle in profit terms etc
but when you look at behind the scenes
what nestle is doing
there's a massive expansion of
distribution network
uh there's more than four percentage
points
to sales
equivalent reduction in expenditure
and hence the operating efficiencies
which have been derived in the last
three years right so this is roughly 150
bips
ebitda margin support from operating
efficiencies annually
in the last three years through
sweating the assets harder and a lot of
uh systems and processes being put in
place by suresh narrator's management
team uh at the ground level on the front
end uh and very recently they
commissioned a state-of-the-art
manufacturing plant where
where
productivity is 20 percent higher than
their other uh plants in the rest of the
country and hence uh asset terms are
rising hence free cash flow is not so
much of a concern uh although revenue
growth has been only 10 11 12 over the
last couple of years which perhaps is is
uh is putting an overhang on the on the
share price hdfc bank uh some of you
might know
uh the common reasons why people uh
people are a little worried on hdfc bank
is the mobile application crashed a
couple of times last year
there was a leadership change
i think 18 months ago
there was a recent quarterly result
announcement when net interest margins
saw a little bit of moderation etc but
behind the scenes we see hdfc bank
significantly gaining market share
around both loan book
as well as deposits and profit after tax
compounding at a very healthy pace with
uh with one of the leading returns on
equity uh amongst lenders especially
amongst banks of this bank being
maintained
right and hence is not a this is not a
company which has
gone through a stagnation and
fundamentals is just a stagnation in the
the share price uh likewise for htfc
life right uh uh you can you read the
text here massive fundamental
progression but the share price hasn't
done much
right now uh
the only thing that we've not addressed
in this
sort of narrative so far
is that
somebody might be questioning that every
time is it possible that the stagnation
happens because of overvaluation that
the the stock becomes so richly valued
that stagnation is around the corner
can't we do something about it can't we
exit when stocks become overvalued now
if they were becoming overvalued we
would be concerned but i think in the
last webinar
we explained this chart in particular in
greater detail i'll summarize it here
when you look at the price to free cash
flow multiples over the last seven years
for these companies
there has been no expansion
in the in the price to free cash flow
multiples here these companies have not
seen
uh any increase in their valuation
metrics provided you're looking at the
right metric
over the last six or seven years where
they have seen an expansion in valuation
matrix is if you do pe multiple price to
earnings right but because the earnings
growth of these companies tends to lag
behind free cash flow growth by five six
percent in every five ten fifteen twenty
year time period historically
uh
the the the pe multiple
obviously sees the numerator being
driven off free cash flows because
that's the only way valuations get
defined whereas the denominator
is driven off earnings and earnings uh a
lag behind free cash flow compounding by
five six percent consistently as working
capital uh cycles keep going down for
these companies asset turns keep going
up for these companies through
technology investments that they do to
make the business a lot more efficient
right um so it is not the case that fy21
which is the end point of all of these
charts it is not the case that fy 21 had
been
a time period of or a time stamp of
overvalued share prices because of which
over the last year and a half the likes
of the likes of nestle hdfc bank hdfc
live and many other companies have have
sort of they can be blamed to have gone
on a holiday uh for some time right so
so that's what's happening on the
valuations front and hence this is the
performance
we are not worried because the
underlying fundamentals
are
are healthy on an absolute basis
uh clients who've stayed with us for one
year two year three years since
inception they would have got a very
healthy return for every such time
period right including the last one year
fifteen percent after the
the the recent uh
sort of under performance is is not a is
not a bad uh outcome in an absolute
manner and when it comes to the under
performance of the last six months
particularly so this is an updated
attribution chart of nifty
again just to summarize this point which
we made in some of our previous
presentations when you look at the nifty
half of nifty 50 has has seen stocks to
12 15 20 30 increases in the share
prices over the last uh
six months and all of these stocks which
have delivered the great results in
their share prices over the last six
months have been uh in commodities and
utilities right uh pgci adani ports cold
india ntpc these are not the kind of
companies that we would want to own in
our consistent compounders portfolio
because their fundamentals do not
compound consistently they don't have a
high pricing power which can deliver
sustainable greatness and sustainable
high free cash generation
over longer term and hence even in
hindsight we wouldn't have done anything
different
to have
to have got these stocks into our
portfolio
any mediocre or higher quality
fundamentals would be sitting in the
chart on the left at the bottom
bottom half
delivering a negative share price return
which is what has led to the
i think 300 basis points 340 basis
points of
negative alpha that you can see here
where in the last six months we've
delivered minus six percent versus nifty
of minus three percent
right so the three percent negative
alpha that you see is largely all
all because of utilities and commodities
doing well in the index which are which
are not the kind of stocks that we would
like to hold in our consistent
compounders portfolio
so um
and yeah this is a quick summary again
not the first time that we are going
through this sort of a phenomenon um a
demonetization period was very similar
it's the same list of indulgal india
tata steel ongc and tbc which led to
uh nifty delivering a
eight percent nine percent better
performance compared to our portfolio
weighted average
uh
for for for a very similar type of a mix
of stocks doing well or not doing well
in the in the broader market um the
demolitization period was temporary
and we believe this last six month
period is also temporary and uh and
since the underlying fundamentals are
compounding uh at actually an
accelerated manner
compared to what they used to previously
we are quite quite comfortable and
confident of
of uh holding on to these companies and
compounding the wealth of our clients
through this portfolio
um so i'll stop here
um and uh and request me
sort of highlight any questions that we
would have got
sure so thank you rakshit uh you know we
already have started receiving a lot of
queries i will again request
participants if you have any queries
please feel free to type it out on q a
box
uh so first uh question is for saurabh
uh saurabh if you are there if you can
hear us
uh
let me hear you
yeah hi sarah so one of our participants
wants to
have your views on on the current market
cycle credit trade cycle and how does it
impact
you know uh the market
and also given you know the fed fed is
increasing the
rates
uh how will it impact you know indian
equity market going forward
so so whilst i'm giving the response
russia given that you've got the
controls you might want to highlight the
blog on the screen which yeah
i wrote about how rising rate cycles
alongside inflation is actually good for
good for consistent compounders
so just some data for people
in the last 70 years since the second
world war
the federal reserve has gone through 12
rate hike cycles right so roughly every
six seven years every six seven years uh
the fed goes through a rate high cycle
right and it's basically the decade long
economic cycle so every six seven years
the fed goes through a rate hike cycle
nothing nothing new there
uh a typical rate hike cycle is
to two percent to two point five percent
uh rate hikes by the fed
uh you will see that the data clearly
shows that out of these twelve rate hike
cycles in
is putting on the screen you can access
it on our website marcellus.in and the
blog will have all of this data
uh in a typical uh out of the 12 rate
hike cycles the fed has done in the in
the last 70 years in 11 of them you had
bull markets at 11 rate hike cycles out
of 12 the market has been rising
focusing specifically on the more recent
rate hike cycles there have been two
rate hike cycles this century by the
federal reserve 2004 to six uh where the
fed hiked by two percent or two point
two five percent
uh uh in that in that two year period
the s p 500 rose 50 the indian stock
market doubled
and 2015 to 17 when the fed again hiked
by around two and a half percent and
again the s p 500
rose by uh rose by around fifty percent
right five zero percent uh if you look
at india uh again this century india has
been through
three
three rate hike cycles and all of them
have been all of them have been
accompanied by rising markets uh so
whether it's in america or in india
rising rate high rising interest rates
typically tend to be accompanied by
rising markets right not by
falling markets which is the narrative
everybody and their mother father is
convincing themselves about now why does
that happen why do
why do higher interest rates uh lead to
why do high why are higher interest
rates accompanied by
by rising markets
typically when the fed hikes rates
they're doing so because economic growth
is is is very hot economic growth is
strong
as a result the economy is overheating
and you have higher inflation and the
fed's job or the reserve bank of india's
job
is to hike rates so that the economy
cools down a bit and the economic
upcycle lasts longer right just to be
clear that's what central bankers are
supposed to do they're supposed to hike
rates when the economy is overheating
take some steam out of inflation so that
the economic upcycle lasts longer that's
what central bankers have paid a salary
to do and that's what they do and
because economic
because rate heights therefore tend to
be accompanied by rising economic growth
which is happening at the moment in our
country you will see
when the
fourth quarter of fi 22 gdp growth comes
through it will be a strong print the
current quarter that we are living
through is also a very strong print on
gdp growth you can see it in gdp growth
you can see it incorporate earnings so
typically because rate hike cycles tend
to be accompanied by strong gdp growth
you get you get pretty punchy bull
markets than the federal reserve high
trade so we got a high state so there's
no there's no great mystery there now
the next level of analysis is to say
what happens to high quality stocks
right high quality stocks of the stock
russia has mentioned
uh what happens to these stocks
when the when
inflation is high gdp growth is high
inflation is high and the fed is hiking
rates and this is where
the the table rushes is put on the
screen will be very useful for you so
what we did was we looked at all the
every single month in this century we
took 22 years of data and roughly
roughly what we figured out was in 40
percent of of the of the time period
this century and 40 of time periods
cpi inflation in india has been above
six percent so again a lot of people
mistakenly believe that high cpi
inflation is somehow rare to india it's
not right by 40 percent of times indian
cpi inflation tends to be uh above six
percent now what you can check and this
is simply looking at the data for the
last 22 years
when cpi inflation is high
companies with strong pricing power
obviously do better right so just to
take an obvious example
if you have high raw material cost
inflation high cpi inflation will a
nation planes do better or will a chota
company do better right it doesn't take
a genius to figure out that the stronger
franchise when destination planes
whether it is a hdfc bank whether it is
a pedolite whether it is a titan whether
it is a nestle a stronger franchise
naturally will have superior pricing
power right and therefore that's what
you see on the screen when inflation is
high when cpi inflation is
is above six percent uh uh uh uh our
type of companies ccp type of companies
tend to outperform the nifty on top line
growth they're basically passing on the
input cost inflation better than a
weaker company they tend to have they
tend to do better than the nifty on top
line growth uh because they hike prices
more uh they tend to do better than the
nifty on bottom line growth right
operating margin improvements are
operating margin holds up better and
russia has previous webinar actually
showed you that that asian prince's
gross margins hold up beautifully when
crude prices double right so strong
companies greater pricing pass greater
defense
of operating margins and companies end
up uh beating the nifty uh through the
course of high inflation periods right
so the data is very clear both at the
macro level
just missing out if you're stressing
stressing about the market going into
meltdown mode we can't we can't stop you
from stressing but we we are we are paid
to be rational
and therefore we are fairly relaxed
about the fact that the fed is hiking
rates we think the fed is doing the
right thing the rvi is doing the right
thing and we have no reason to believe
the sorts of companies we are investing
in will fall apart uh obviously there
are at any in any country in any country
in any bull market you will have low
quality companies
companies that actually don't make any
money
they pretend to make money but actually
they don't make money they simply
survive by raising fresh capital from
investors those companies will suffer
their share prices will fall you will
see bankruptcies from them promoters
will run away it's happened in america
before it will happen in america again
it's happened in india before it'll
happen in india again but i don't think
those of you are on this call invest in
those sorts of junk stocks
you guys are investing in good quality
companies and
economic growth is solid corporate
corporate performance is coming through
you see every day you can see corporate
results coming through at a rock solid
rate so so history suggests common sense
suggests data such as current uh
corporate results suggest
that rising rate hike cycles
high quality companies tend to do very
well
thanks thanks sarah
rakshit next question is for you
one of our participant
is the participants are asking or is
asking
you know how do we know uh the holiday
period has started and what should be
our behavior you know at that point of
time and also if there is any trend to
know how long it will last sure so um
how do we know the holiday period has
started well we can know only in
hindsight uh it's very difficult to know
about it in foresight that it is going
to start tomorrow we can only know in
hindsight after a few months have
progressed where shared price doesn't do
much despite the fact that fundamentals
are roaring ahead
um
what should we do during the holiday
period
so
i'll give you an example of what we've
done
in some of these cases so
uh as we showed that dr lal path labs
and it's uh it's worth actually
uh
trying to live through that
that holiday period of doctoral path
labs so many of you who were our clients
back then as well
you would have you would have
experienced
what what i'm reflecting on here
um for a good three year period when we
were managing money on behalf of our
clients dr lal continued to be one of
the larger positions in the portfolio
everything else in the portfolio was
uh tracking fundamentals but dr lal
wasn't
right and since this was one of the
larger allocations it kept
putting a drag
on the on the overall performance of
of the
of the fund in a pro databases now
first of all what we need to be all
right with
is that our fundamentals of dr lal
progressing well that's the first point
of action
we have to we as investors if you've
given your your money to a fund manager
than the fund management team otherwise
if you're doing it yourself then you as
investors you have to dig deep into the
the behind the scenes activity happening
around fundamentals of the
company whose share price has gone on
the holiday period that's the first
action actionable that you have to
think about the second part
is that because the stock is on a
holiday its allocation would have
naturally
gone down
uh if the rest of the portfolio has been
has been going up in that situation
uh provided you are convinced on the
fundamental progress
you should buy more of that stock right
because due to the holiday period its
allocation must have
gone down in the portfolio and that's an
opportune moment to uh
do an increase make an increase in the
allocation in the portfolio probably by
by shaving off a little bit of stocks
which have gone up
we've done this in the last couple of
months in our ccp portfolio uh with some
stocks we've done this
uh two years ago uh through rebalancing
of bajaj finance we've done this
uh
during the dr lal path labs
holding period of 2017 to 2019 middle
those two and a half year period when we
were we were managing funds on behalf of
our clients and dr lal was on the
holiday period you have to do this you
have to benefit from the opportunity uh
the benefit from the opportunity
then then happens when the holiday
period ends and the stock catches up
with fundamentals because the higher
location
that
you gave to that stock by buying more of
it during holidays it leads to a higher
uh share price return and hence in the
longer run uh the kind of performance
that we have for instance uh delivered
in the fund right the since inception
since inception 21.5 22 percent the
three year 23 performance that you see
this includes a three-year holiday of dr
lal uh
over the over three and a half year
period uh needless to say it also
includes the last one one and a half
year of holiday of hdfc bank nestle
hdfc life etc which i discussed so
rather than getting too worried about
the holiday period
there are those two actionables that can
actually benefit from the holiday period
more understand fundamentals and buy
more of the stocks which have been on
holiday and you are convinced about the
fundamentals
uh thanks rakshit another query linked
to it to the answer that you gave one of
the participants are asking what do you
do during the holiday periods to make
yourself comfortable that these
companies will deliver going forward in
terms of fundamental checks what are the
things that you do
right so um i mean the things that we do
are
[Music]
nothing different honestly speaking
nothing different from what we would do
even when the stock is not on a holiday
period just that we would we would
prioritize stuff for stocks on a holiday
period to ensure that
we benefit
in a in a more proactive manner
from any such opportunity so what do we
do for with dr lars just to give you
that example of three year long holiday
what were we doing at that time
uh we spoke to
many
uh
laboratory managers as in the
franchisees any franchisees who would be
running in different cities
uh few collection centers of thyrocare
tarot care was launching a massive price
war few collection centers of srl and
few collections in terms of dr lal right
this was typically north india because
at that time dr lal's footprint was
largely in north india east india was
still uh yet to become yet to become big
and players like metropolis vijaya
diagnostics etc which you see in the
listed universe come they were not
present in north india in a in a big
proportion so these were the three
competitors
we tried to understand from uh
from
the the people in the ecosystem whether
they be collection center franchisee
managers
franchisee laboratory managers
speaking to doctors who in effect are
aware of which lab is
doing well in their local geographies
and
also speaking to firms such as an abort
not the listed entity but the unlisted
entity which provides reagents and
reagents and testing material to uh
to the
uh
to the diagnostic players through all of
these checks what we figured out was
that while thyrocare has put its dengue
test at some 80 rupees versus doctor 200
rupee and there's a massive price for
out there
customer footfall
is still
sticking with dr lal and dr lal is
expanding its footprint
only because it is offering a faster
turnaround time to the customer than
thyrocare which matters more to the
customer than just a cheaper price and
dr lar is is running a hub and spoke
model
to to build its brand presence within
the pull pull of the footfalls rather
than many of its competitors who were
sort of giving
something called as cuts to the doctors
in order to incentivize the doctor to uh
to push the patients to go to their labs
right dr lal was not doing any of that
in north india at that time and that
gave us a conviction that look if dr lal
is getting the volume of footfalls and
the network expansion
without driving or incentivizing the
medical fraternity right then
then there is obviously
there is obviously nothing we should be
too worried about there is no there is
no lack of pricing power here with dr
lal market share is maintained and
growing
and the share price performance is
probably because of non-fundamental
factors uh that's i think this is uh let
me just use a cricket analogy to explain
this so folks if you believe that
that say
uh
is fundamentally a good player right
he's had a couple of bad twos but he's
fundamentally a good player when we see
that he's having a bad run of form
right in the in the purana
80s the selectors would drop a pujara
saying he's a couple of bad tools we
can't deal with a player like this let's
just drop them
in the last decade or so what the indian
team management has done is what russia
is talking about going to stocks right
the indian team management says this is
fundamentally a high-class player
he's delivered for india for a long
period of time so rather than dropping
him let's send him one in india a2
uh send a one in india a2 or in
case of
send him to a county cricket
uh uh send him on a tour which will
challenge his skills which will allow
him to get which will allow us to gauge
whether he's actually a consistent
compounder or is he was his past
performance and aberration right was he
just lucky in the past uh uh or is he
actually consistent we've seen the bcci
do this quite quite regularly now in the
last few years where they where rather
than dropping a high-class player rather
than churning the portfolio they say
let's
having faith monitor the player monitor
the player rakshas
analogy here is doing more channel
checks talking to competitors copying
talking to labs
because we can see that this is
fundamentally a high class compounding
machine and and just as in cricket so as
in uh
in investment if you want to benefit
from rahul dravid's 15-year compounding
at a test average of 55 and as sachin
tendulkar's 20 year compounding at a
test average of 53 uh you can't say
what's up every bad series no i'll drop
you you know if you've taken a holiday
of a year i'm sorry you're out right if
you had a two or on the other verse the
way many indian fundamentalists think uh
you played well for two series uh uh
rahul or sachin but two good series
i'll drop you right we don't do that for
a nonsense we know this is a drawing we
know this is a sachin we know this is a
legend this is fundamentally a
consistent compounder we stick with them
over long periods of time low portfolio
chart when they go through compounding
holidays when they go through a lean run
off
you send them on a like
has currently gone to county cricket you
watch them make sure that on their on
their while they're having a poor runner
form fundamentally their batting skills
are intact and then you benefit from the
fact that that uh uh the holiday will
end and once again
will score 100 for india once again all
the all three names and on the screen in
front of us will compound for us right
so the holiday is actually a good time
for you to do more work
reassess the players skills reassess the
compounded skills we've got more than
abundant resources as a country bcci
you've got the vcc has got more than
abundant resources to check out players
skills and marcellus has more than
abundant resources to validate that that
nestle uh uh dr lal hdfc live are indeed
powerhouse compounders uh uh dr lal hdfc
bank
and hence the faith and hence the faith
honestly without any nerds right our own
money our entirety of our savings
is also riding on these portfolios and
we don't really feel nervous about it we
feel very very reassured that our monies
are invested in these companies and we
know that
we will get we will get super returns on
our portfolio because of the quality of
the franchises that you are staring at
on the screen
uh uh vinit is asking in in the
increasing interest rate scenario
uh what is the impact on banks you know
their balance sheet their growth their
margins
what's your view on that
so typically what happens is when you
begin a new
economic cycle typically when you begin
a new economic cycle
central bank cuts rates money market
conditions are full flush with cash uh
in that sort of circumstance right when
the market has lots of liquidity
the weaker lenders and the stronger
lenders are on an even footing you have
market me lots of liquidity
a wholesale market funded bank
uh wholesale market funded banks
concierge
bank
industry bank has also high wholesale
funding the bank is very high on funding
even a wholesale market funded bank ends
up having low cost of funds and can give
an hdfc bank which is a terrific a
low-cost casa
current and savings account funding
franchise so in in when the
when the economic cycle begins and the
market is flush with the money market is
flush with liquidity the gap in funding
cost between strong banks
and and weak banks isn't as high as it
should be
and that's why uh what's happened two
days ago is terrific for for high
quality lenders right uh uh
an hdfc banker codetech bank average
finance or if we take our
things of capital portfolio and access
bank these guys are very strong
liability franchises
and therefore as liquidity titans
the weaker the weaker lenders in india
will have a disproportionate jump in
their cost of funding weaker lenders
funding costs will jump far more sharply
than hdfc banks will and and as it is as
the as you can see on the screen hdfc
bank is as it is pulling away market
share hand over fist if you add up all
the private sector lenders in the
country plus sbi the rest of the banking
system together hasn't gained as much
market share as hdfc bank has done on
both sides of the balance sheet in the
last three years and as the rbi tightens
liquidity
that market share gained by atfc banks
should accelerate further and ditto for
ditto for a kotak bank which also has a
very strong casa franchise
indeed for access bank which also has a
very strong grasa franchise and for
bajaj finance which doesn't have a casa
franchise for a bank but it has a very
strong
liability franchise after hdfc bajaj has
the strongest liability franchise
amongst non-banks in the country so the
men and the boys separate the woman and
the girls separate right it becomes
easier to discern
as the rbi tightens liquidity and
that's why we are you know we are uh
hoping that shaktidasi titles liquidity
is super fast over the next six months
so that
we can do scope
thanks thanks
uh but actually we have few specific
queries on individual companies and we
can go one by one the first is on dr lal
performance
it has obviously foreign
is it because of you know increasing
competitive uh uh competi increasing
competition with new players entering
with more you know hospital opening up
you know
testing in-house what's your view on
that
right so um it's actually quite the
reverse
it's non-fundamental reasons because
when we talk about fundamentals we can
only see incremental strength
uh of of dr lal
right uh
progressively
so let me highlight
our reading of the situation at the
ground level as the way it is
progressing
for dr lala's business over the last 12
months
um what uh what kovit has done is it has
given three types of opportunities to dr
lal the first opportunity
was to
acquire suburban and expand footprint in
west india right now uh suburban before
dr lal's acquisition was not a very
efficient
franchise
and uh
anybody would be right to say that this
was not a this was not a high high
return on capital employed asset that
that dr lyles acquired but dr lal didn't
acquire server one further for the
efficiency of the business they acquired
suburban for the footprint that bourbon
already has
in the state of maharashtra particularly
right they've got around 45 odd
laboratories and a reasonable enough
footprint of uh
of of market share of footfalls
where in healthcare for a doctor law to
expand organically into the west and
south india it would have been a
very daunting task it would have been a
significant challenge because healthcare
healthcare is quite a regional concept
right trust building takes a very long
time and it's not a short period of time
where you can leverage on
presence in north and east india and
suddenly expand in western south india
right so organic would have been very
slow burn for dr lal here suburban was
available
during the covet times and dr lal was
was
holding on to more than thousand crores
of unutilized cash on the balance sheet
waiting for such an acquisition and
through this acquisition now
i think there'll be massive synergies in
terms of first of all footprint
expansion invest
using suburban's existing network and
secondly uh operating efficiencies which
dr lal is very good at suburban hadn't
been good at
and and we should see benefits of that
flowing through so that's one the second
piece that has happened in the last 12
months is
the expansion of uh
tier two tier 3 city presence of dr lal
through partnership model with mom and
pop labs so
um
effectively what's happening is the mom
and pop labs across the country are
facing a massive threat from two sides
one pan-india players such as dr lal
metropolis thyrocare srl etc increasing
their footprint and secondly
new entrants who are
either the pharma companies i think a
couple of pharma companies have
announced their interests have expressed
their interest
launching diagnostic firms by saying
that look we already have
some reach with the doctors through our
pharma business why not we also open
laboratories diagnostics
to to capitalize on that reach what dr
lyle is saying is that look rather than
me being
me as dr lal being another
uh source of competition for you mom and
pop lab owners
let me partner with you right so you
become my partner franchisee where
you as a mom and pop lab retain the
footfalls retain the doctor relationship
in the local area
and i will give you a wider list of
tests on the menu card with shorter
turnaround times because my laboratory
network uh allows you to deliver reports
uh much quicker compared to previously
where these mom and pop labs would have
sent warriors of samples
to the nearest metro city or tier one
city
outsourced large laboratory and deliver
the sample results after a couple of
days to the
to the customer for high-end tests here
dr lal is offering even high-end tests
on single-day turnaround time
uh
and the third piece they are offering uh
to through the partnership is uh the the
customer interface
uh through the mobile app the website
the report generation in soft copy so on
and so forth
so effectively mom and pop lab becomes
the front end for dr lal
with their current footfall market share
in the local areas
without facing a significant threat of
competition from new entrants
right so that's helping dr lal that's
helping some of these franchisees
and and hence
in fact over the last two years when you
look at december 21 revenue of dr lal
over december 19.
non-covet organic without suburban in it
without covait in it dr lar's growth has
been 17
metropolis zero uh uh thyrocare is zero
right so these are these are numbers i'm
reading out from the reported results dr
lal 17 annualized growth
requires zero and metropolis zero
over december 19 to december 21. this is
market share gain in front of our eyes
which is happening at a much more
accelerated pace than what it used to be
prior to cohen
then another piece that dr lal is is
gradually doing is expand the home
sample collection concept in smaller
cities
by leveraging on the fact that during
the covert times smaller cities were
forced to
force to experience home sample
collection as a concept
uh which was not
facing much of adoption which was not
receiving much of adoption try to prove
it because people will just pick up
their activa and give their blood and
urine sample at the nearby laboratory
end
and come back and in the evening go and
collect the printout of the report from
the laboratory and make the payment
there right so that used to be the
standard approach
now kovit
sort of
forcefully made these households
experience the convenience of home
sample collection and and firms such as
dr lal are capitalizing on this
by investing investing into
infrastructure development around even
non-covet testing with home sample
collection right no other player is
doing it as aggressively as dr lal is
most other players uh had home sample
collection only for covet for two tier
two three four cities dr lar is his head
and shoulders above that in investment
of infrastructure so so this is what we
observe at the ground level market share
gains backed by tangible evidence
of how these gains are happening through
through capital allocation decisions
uh which keeps us convinced so we do
agree
that dr lal has fallen by i think 30 35
in the last three four months
uh and it's one of the one of the weaker
performers in the at the share price
level in our portfolio but we are
actually buying more of it for many of
you as clients you would have seen
in your account statements we bought
more of it at some point in the recent
past
we thank you uh rakshat
another question is on icc lombard we
had recently exited relaxo and entered
icc lombard
even though we have written on
on the rational for it in our newsletter
but if you can you know quickly touch
upon the
long term competitive advantage of icc
longbow
sure so icici lombard is
is actually
prudence of underwriting if i were to
summarize it in one statement now
to explain it in greater detail this is
a general insurer
right in in general insurance
typically industry-wide combined ratios
tend to hover around
over around 100 to 110 which means
most general insurers they actually lose
money on the underwriting front right
what i see i say lombard
does is by being prudent its combined
ratios are the lowest
in fact at many times it actually makes
a profit on the underwriting front
itself
right now beyond the underwriting piece
the next piece is around
around investment income which drives
the fundamentals of uh insurance
companies right so so that's the
business model where icici lombard first
of all contains the combined ratios and
delivers underwriting uh profitability
compared to losses for many of the
industry participants
it's it's around their choice of which
line of business
they want to get into
uh so
there would be times when isis lombard
will decide
to not enter let's say crop insurance
there would be times like these when
they've
when they've sort of uh expanded into uh
into into some new lines of business uh
this timing of entry and exit uh done
once in three four years around lines of
businesses
uh it helps icici and lombard actually
not chase revenue growth without profits
they chase revenue growth with uh
marginal underwriting profit so that's a
that's the first piece the second piece
is that uh
more than a third more than a third of
icici lombard's
business is motor right uh motor
insurance uh that two measure bulk of it
being uh private cars
uh right in two wheelers and in motor
insurance what this firm does
by
reaching out to the oems
and ensuring that at the point of sale
icici lombard taps into the customer
base in a far more aggressive manner
than anybody else
any of you would have bought
cars more recently
most of you would have gotten icici
lombard policy with it in the last two
three years it's a phenomenal
monopolization of oem level uh a
insurance
policy sale to a new customer and then
i say lombard
it tracks the data of
behavior uh on the on the claims that
they received from the customer base
in a far more rigorous manner than
anybody else right uh
so there will be
there will be a lot of tracking on
things like no claim bonus before they
uh before they agree to
uh sort of service a claim uh whether no
claim bonus really genuinely uh was
deserved or not as in in the previous
year was there a claim or not before
they agreed to service a claim so on and
so forth and issuing policies and prices
uh of issuance of policies on renewal
basis claim history most companies which
are more sales oriented right they don't
focus on whether the customer has had a
good or bad
experience of claims
without considering that sort of an
underwriting piece most insurance
companies are just after getting market
share of of renewal premiums right
that's not what icici lombard does and
hence whether it be the oem level or
renewal
it's a it's a much higher quality
of customer base that they end up
sitting with right
so these are some of the competitive
advantages more recently now uh in order
to accelerate growth they've
they've made aggressive entry into
uh into uh into health care into
commercial vehicle insurance etc
and
excite life sorry
bharti aksa
was
was an asset that they acquired over the
last couple of years
to expand their footprint there as well
and and that adds extra muscle to their
distribution capabilities going forward
so uh so that's uh that's largely the
the reason why let me just throw in my
10 cents there
as i as i
in a car which is uh insured by ics a
lombard for the last three years uh why
because
the toyota dealership from which i
bought the car
uh has been completely monopolized by
icsa onboard so many years back 15 years
ago rakshasana used to cover a stock in
the uk called admiral
which was the uk's leading motor insurer
still is actually uh in fact russia was
the top three insurance analyst in the
uk on the back of his insurance coverage
including admiral and one of the things
we saw there was how admiral used
analytics to build a leadership position
in motor insurance the closest we can
see to anybody uh building leadership
and analytics in india leadership in
motor insurances is islam
we can't see any other private sector
insurer with anything like this set of
competencies in motor underwriting
and in distribution of a distribution of
policies and as i should said that's
validated by
superior profitability the the other
interesting areas as russian mentioned
the ceo is very aggressively pushing
into health care so this afternoon paige
was doing a
channel a primary data call with with a
large broker so so five years ago the
insurance regulator changed the
regulations around the brokerage of
insurance and the regulator created
something called the
point of sale point of sale agent uh
ilom is very adeptly using this new
regulatory construct to enter health
insurance
aggressively
they will be challenged by a couple of
players there but this is what our
research is suggesting uh basis uh the
strengths of this house uh we think that
they'll do a very good job in and the
motor they're already the best in the
business a lot of people superficially
compare them to other weaker players in
motor and we don't think that any
comparison either on profitability or an
underwriting strength or on analytics in
health there are other people ahead of
islam but uh given what we are finding
out in our channel checks we think i
alone has a very good chance of
building if not the largest perhaps the
second largest private sector franchise
in insurance
thanks sarah uh so next question uh is
on our view
of hdfc bank and uh hdfc and uh will
will these talks with these talks go on
you know holidays if we have any of you
you know if till the time you think i
will just cover few
housekeeping stuff
one of the participants have asked do we
have top-up you know can we can we
top-up yes you can top-up minimum top-up
amount is five flags you know you can
just transfer and give us the funding
proof if you're an existing client
obviously
also one of the participants are asking
i'm worried investing entire money lump
sum
can we stagger yes you can stagger we
have stp option
where whereby your 50 lakhs that you
that you transfer to us
will be invested in five branch over
five months 10 lakh will be immediately
deployed in the market
balance 40 lakh would be parked in
liquid funds hdfc overnight and every
month on 20th 10 lakh will be
transferred and invested in equity so
five months five tranches
and you know as an investor you have one
option suppose market correct by 10 15
you know in next one month and you feel
this is the right time to enter to enter
uh or to invest the balance lump sum you
can tell us and we will deploy the
balance money left in the liquid fund
and also
one of the participants have asked i
have i've already invested with you guys
uh i want to invest regularly is there
an sap plan yes we do have an sap plan
we will reach out to you uh
you know in for an existing client
existing investor
they have to sign up for sap and every
month
money will be debited from your bank
account and invested in the equity
market
uh so sorry if you can answer uh
you know the query on htfc bank
and hdfc merger and so we want to go for
it
sure sir
so um look i mean um
first and foremost and and i'll talk as
hdfc bank shareholders first i mean we
are shareholders our clients are
shareholders
of
sdfc bank so um the first and foremost
benefit of this is that hdfc banks so
far had a very small market share in
in home loans right home loans has been
has been
probably the smallest part of hdfc banks
book compared to any other any other
large private sector bank so
because of that hdfc bank's retail book
it runs off
it runs off faster
when compared with some of the other
larger uh private sector banks now
uh just to do some rough uh rough maths
here
in order to
grow
hdfc banks loan book by 20
hdfc bank has to disburse
around 60 65 percent of its
beginning of the year
loan book size during the next 12 months
right so let's say as we're talking
about fy 23
whatever was the loan book size on 31st
march 2022
in the next 12 months hdfc bank would
have had to disburse
60 percent of the 31st march 2022 loan
book size in order to grow its long book
by 20 why is that because 40 percent
of the loan book of htfc bank runs off
every 12 months
why does it run off so so quickly
because of the absence of home loans
because of the absence of home loans in
the large part of the loan book the
tenure the tale of the
loan book
is very short
and hence
uh the the rate at which in effect i
mean it's like to give you an to give an
analogy in order to drive a car at say
50 kilometers per hour speed uh hdfc has
to has to drive it in in only
the second or third gear right
other banks they drive they drive the
same 50 kilometer per hour speed car
in fourth gear and some of them in fifth
gear because they don't have to disburse
uh 60 65 percent of their loan book
in order to deliver 20 loan book growth
they have to only disburse 30 of the
loan book in order to grow their loan
book by 20
um so edition of home loans
uh has a larger proportion of the loan
book for hdfc bank after the merger
it actually brings in significantly more
efficiencies to the
to the uh uh sort of machinery of uh of
htfc bank so that's that's the first
part the second part is home loans are
also the fastest growing segment of
uh of retail loans uh in the country
right and
and and because hdfc bank wasn't doing a
large part of it its market share in
home loans was barely i think two
percent
compared to icici bank access bank all
of them their market share being seven
nine ten eleven percent hdfc banks
market share was two percent despite the
fact that as a bank it's a much larger
bank than any icici bank access bank
etc right um adding on the home loan
portfolio
uh
after the merger
gives a phillip to the rate at which
loan book will compound because this is
the largest this is the fastest growing
segment of retail loans right
the next bit is the ability to cross
sell
to hdfc limited customers 70 percent of
whom don't have
hdfc bank casa right so so all the
current account saving accounts of hdfc
limited customers 70 of them are not
with hdfc bank right now when the entity
has been merged together
the ability to
sort of drive casa through
through the hdfc limited customer base
is a very good low hanging fruit
available and low cost of funding like
casa
is is gold dust for
for any bank to to deliver high
high margin growth in the years to come
so that's in effect the benefit of the
merged entity to htfc bank shareholders
and although the most recent reported
results
and whatever 100 basis points of net
interest margin compression because of
wholesale book for htfc bank growing a
little faster etc led to the share price
reflecting continuation of the holiday
period for another couple of months
cannot do not quite
so we want to add something to it
why don't you just project the
newsletter
[Music]
again folks all of this is available for
you on our website just go to
marcellus.com and you'll see lucidly
lucidly laid out the arguments that
russia just presented to you the maths
is actually extremely simple a lot of
people complicate things needlessly
in our profession
both entities hdfc limited
and hdfc bank
both of them are lenders who make a two
percent roi two percent roa in india one
for lenders of the scale is spectacular
both are spectacular entities just to
give you a sense of how spectacular
these lenders are
in the last 40 years
the last 40 years htfc hdfc limited's
credit cost has been two bips two bips
is the ultimate right off they've
suffered on a 40 year portfolio that is
truly spectacular right it's a very high
quality book uh rakshas also explained
to you that uh hdfc bank is growing like
a rocket both sides of the balance sheet
and he's also showed you
and the newsletter that he's been
cleaning up i'll give you more details
the hdfc bank has gained more share in
the last three years than the rest of
the banking system combined right so
both entities are two percent roa
entities which means very profitable
hdfc bank is growing like a rocket far
faster than any other bank on a
three-year basis uh if you merge two
entities which have two percent roa
even if you take some amount of
acquisition merger cost and some rbi
interventions on
crr psl and so on even then once you
bake in some synergies you're back to
two percent roa two two businesses both
of them are two percent roa you merge
them you end up back at two percent roa
now the difference is
at the moment because hdfc bank doesn't
have a mortgage book of any meaningful
size it gears up hdfc banks debt equity
is nine times right so two percent roa
multiplied by nine times that equity
gives you a 17 18 roe bank so hdfc bank
today two percent roa multiplied by nine
gives you a 17 18 rod bank
uh uh uh on uh on a mortgage book once
you have once a bank has a mortgage book
the rbi has lower capital adequacy
ratios on a mortgage book and hence post
merger hdfc bank should comfortably be
able to do 10 times that equity so roa
stays the same as today two percent roa
we're not assuming any jump in ro i
think that's a very conservative
assumption to say are we saying
you multiply the gearing not by nine but
by 10 because rbi has lower capital
adequacy charges
on on a mortgage book you end up with a
20 rv bank right so the merged entity
will be a more profitable bank on a roa
basis as raksha explained it will grow
faster
uh uh and as we already showed you the
data already shows in the last three
years no other bank has been able to
match uh
the growth engine that this is bank
right this is why working in the stock
market in india is such a privilege
you're getting giant entities
gobbling up massive industries like
banking in broad daylight and you're
getting a compounding holiday which is
why these compounding holidays are are
great opportunities for us to invest
money in outstanding franchises
franchises which have proven themselves
not over 10 years not over 20 years over
40 years they've proven themselves in
fact
for yesterday i sold my father's flat in
delhi which was financed 40 years ago
with an hdfc limited home loan
and over those 40 years
thankfully my father repaid his loan but
as i said two vips credit card suggests
htfc limited has done a spectacular job
so two great firms merging the stock
market has pulled back the stock price
by 15
uh
[Music]
these companies in which we invest are
already large
do they have enough opportunity to
become even bigger i think we have
touched upon in one of our note and uh
vikaji also has given example of fission
paint you know which if it continues to
compound at 20 25
for next 20 years it will become four
five trillion dollar company uh is it
possible
right uh
okay so on asian pains i would say valid
concern on the others this concern is
actually not valid so so let me give you
some data
um
so first companies other than asian
paints
dr lal path labs is five percent of
diagnostic industry market share
right
now although it is
one-third of
uh
pan-india organized players market share
organized players
have been growing by leaps and bounds
and the 15 percent of market share of
organized is certainly going to go
towards 25 35 45 market share
in the in the years and decades to come
right so for a doctoral path lab the
ability to grow market share from
from five percent
to uh
to a double digit number and then to a
very high double digit number
this is uh
this is not not
difficult provided it remains a great
quality franchise so the runway is long
titan is six percent market share in
jewelry
um
companies such as say
hdfc bank bajaj finance right bajaj
finance market share in lending is two
percent
hdfc banks market share in lending is
nine or ten percent
right uh
when you look at ici lombard uh
hdfc life their market shares are
are less than 10 percent each in the
entire insurance industry right
in some cases
the
the the market share gain opportunities
from psu
banks psu insurers
public sector weaker competitors
in other cases
the the opportunity to gain market share
is from unorganized players right let's
say a jewelry
mom and pop labs in diagnostics
page industries market share even in
men's innerwear
uh is only
um and if you if you consider women's
inner where it's only eight percent if
you consider page industries and market
share in leisure which is half of pages
revenues it's it's low single digits
right so so that's the
that's the length of the runway in front
of all of these companies it is far from
a point where we would be worried about
stagnation because of saturation
stagnation of growth because of
saturation in market shares
for any of these companies now having
said that as i said valid
comment made on on companies such as a
pd lite or in in white glue asian paints
in paints so asian paints is already 50
55 market share for the last five six
years
in the organized paint industry pedolite
has been for the last couple of decades
more than 90 percent market share of
white blue right it's a monopoly uh
fairway call and hence what about these
types of companies so learning from pity
light first the answer to this and i'll
explain the answer on asian pains
why has pity light not stagnated despite
the fact that even two decades ago
its market share had maxed out in
fevicol why has the company not
stagnated in
in its revenue growth right it is
because
today
uh a fever call
is less than a quarter
of peter lights revenues
right the remaining three quarters is
something that never existed till two
decades ago right things such as a
doctor fix it raw
all the acquisitions of mc land steel
grip etc that were done 15 17 years ago
organic expansion of
a fabric adhesive uh
the the the home diy
uh adhesives uh for art and craft so on
and so forth right a variety of things
pedalite has done in the last couple of
decades which have added new revenue
growth drivers for this business and
hence i have not let the
uh let the market share in february
become a reason for stagnation in growth
right or fundamentals asian pains
interestingly is doing the same
five or six years ago you could have
argued asian paints was only a paint
company not anymore not anymore at all
because
uh putty
primers
uh waterproofing
these are
three products in which asian paints has
already made it big
from being non-existent in these
industries till five six years ago
right
more interestingly
now it is transitioning into becoming a
service offering uh uh right something
called uh asian paints home decor
asian paints beautiful home solution
right through combination of brick and
mortar retail format of ap homes where
they've got in-house sanitary wear
in-house modular kitchens in-house
electrical sorry lighting
in-house door frames
as offerings and they are offering it
under the under the retail umbrella of
ap ohms and then packaging it up with
the service offering of uh
organized architect as a service through
asian paints beautiful home solutions
for some of you who don't know anything
about this just to highlight some
numbers
uh
our rough sense is
a high single digit to closer to 10
of of current revenues of asian paints
if not more if not more than 10
are being generated from all of these uh
parts of
of home decor
uh services put together right you won't
see this in revenue of sleek and ss
which are reported as
two home decor separate categories in
their reported results because some of
these
sales of services and products actually
go directly into into the standalone
entity of asian paints and are not
reported separately right
sleek and ss are only four five percent
of revenue there's a lot more that
they're already doing this is more than
10 right so
the way we see it is asian paints is no
more just a paint company five six years
ago it was ten years down the line paint
will be probably as small
as uh as let's say men's inner wear for
page industries today's which used to be
the only thing paige used to do till two
decades ago
as small as fevicol is for pedolite
which used to be the only thing
pedialyte used to do 25 years ago as
small as
bajaj finances consumer durables
lending which used to be the only thing
bajaj finance used to do 10 years ago
right
people used to ask about bajaj finances
stagnation of growth because consumer
durable lending market share for bajaj
finance caused
nearing saturation it was a valid
concern if you didn't look beyond
consumer variables but bajaj finance
looked beyond consumer durables in a
massive way
today it's hardly 10 of the overall loan
book of bajaj finance right so that's
how these businesses evolve they don't
allocate capital by staying the same old
same old always
right if the industries within which
they operate
are
relatively smaller or they have become
too big in those industries these
businesses they allocate capital
in concentric circles to add on to
adjacencies and do more with the same
sort of infrastructure to grow beyond
the core
right so that's uh that's what asian
paints we delight bajaj finance solution
to
market share
saturation related question is
and thank you rakshit uh we will just
take last query for the day and i will
take it
so one of our participants says you know
i i love marcelo's philosophy thank you
so much for posting uh doing webinars
and writing books
and given that you tell us everything
why should we invest with you and not
manage it on our own
so answer is very simple uh you know
the reason why we write books you know
we do webinars we write newsletter
is is to is to tell the world what we
are doing what we are thinking if anyone
has you know patience energy to follow
us
i think that's the best way to do uh uh
you know manage your money on your own
but if you're doing you know if you're
busy in your life
in your professional life
in your business and you want
professionals to manage your money and
that's where you know our role comes in
picture we will continue to post we will
continue to write uh you know give a
share whatever we learn to all up with
all our participants thank you so much
thank you saurabh thank you raksha thank
you thank you
everybody thank you